<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
    <p>You have found yourself on the home page of a project in mathematics. What some people think math is can be very different than what other people think, so we need to make some things clear right away. This is a project in <em>abstract</em> math, which you may or may not have explicit experience with. Fear not: we will not be delving into lofty and difficult concepts on this site. Instead we are interested more in discovering what math looks like to people who have fallen in love with it. Yes, we exist, and we can be normal people too -- math is beautiful if you catch it in the right light.</p>
    <p>Everybody has at some point enjoyed something which a mathematician would consider math. Have you ever solved a problem (not just in the classroom but anywhere in life) by thinking about it, even if it required a few steps to solve? It feels good when a plan works as designed, right? Have you ever enjoyed playing a game according to the rules because following the rules provides a challenge and that is where the fun lies? These images are much more what we mean when talking about math, at least here on this website, than pages and pages of furiously scribbled calculations.</p>
    <p>Let's see an example of the type of math we are talking about here. Suppose we are playing tic-tac-toe. I am X and you are O, the board is as below and it is your turn.</p>
    <table class="tictactoe">
        <tr><td/><td>O</td><td/></tr>
        <tr><td>O</td><td>X</td><td/></tr>
        <tr><td/><td>X</td><td/></tr>
    </table>
    <p>Where do you choose? If you see that choosing the top-left corner will guarantee you a win, then you have just done some abstract math. How do you know that you will win if you choose the top-left corner? If you wanted to be a good sport, would you be able to explain to me why you are certain that you will win? This type of thinking is a large part of what we do when we do math. We see an answer to some question and we try to describe our answer in a way which is irrefutably correct and which others can understand and follow.</p>
    <p>It is this irrefutability of solutions that appeals so much to so many mathematicians. It is not my fault, or yours, that the board above can guarantee you a win. That's just how the game works. Sure, you could say it is my fault (and yours) that the board ended up as above, but that's not the question. The question is that, starting with that particular board, what happens?</p>
    <p>As mathematicians, we can see the outcome of the game <em>before</em> you actually place three Os in a row. The reasoning we perform when understanding this is fundamental logic and basic analysis, and with some simple tools like these we can understand behavior of systems such as this game. In general that's all math is -- seing what things we can be absolutely certain of given some initial information and being able to prove it with basic reasoning.</p>
    <p>We mathematicians like to invent our own problems once we get the hang of it because it can be fun to challenge yourself with your own questions. As we get better, we can change the type of questions we look at too. A large part of math is coming up with the right settings where we can ask the right questions and find neat ways to answer them. The motivation here is self-apparent: we do it because it is fun to do.</p>
    <p>There is another, perhaps less universally familiar, reason that people fall in love with math. As we see more and more of what other mathematicians have come up with, we start seeing connections between branches of math that seemed totally unrelated. Some questions about the best way to tie a knot can be answered with the same tools used to solve combination puzzles like the Rubik's cube. Some calculations which are too complicated to do directly can be done instead with pictures of ways to fold sheets of rubber without cutting the sheets. Many people love math because of the endless connections between what seemed like completely unrelated concepts, and the deeper you go the more connections you find. I promised at the beginning that we wouldn't get into deep topics, though, so we should move on.</p>
</page>